Henry DeWolf Smyth Papers 1885-1987 Mss.Ms.Coll.15
American Philosophical Society
Henry DeWolf Smyth Papers
1885-1987
Mss.Ms.Coll.15
American Philosophical Society
52.5 Linear feet
Best known as author of the "Smyth Report," the official government report on the development of the atomic bomb, Henry DeWolf Smyth had a long and varied career as a physicist, diplomat, instructor, policy maker, and administrator. Taking leave from his position with the Physics Department at Princeton, Smyth began work on the Uranium committee of the National Defense Research Committee in 1940, serving as a consultant on the Manhattan Project from 1943-1945. Although he returned to Princeton after the war, Smyth left academia to become Commissioner of the U.S. Atomic Energy Commission (AEC) from 1949 to 1954, and he subsequently served as U.S. Representative to the International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA), from 1961 to 1970. The Smyth Papers (1885-1987) contain correspondence, subject files, speeches, manuscripts of unpublished and published works, reprints and printed publications, scientific class notes and papers, newspaper clippings, photographs, and memorabilia which document Smyth's career as a physicist and statesman. The bulk of the collection dates from approximately 1944 to 1970, the most active and influential years of his career, providing good documentation of his work on the Manhattan Project and the Smyth Report, and his involvement with the U.S. Atomic Energy Commission and the International Atomic Energy Commission.
Smyth, Henry De Wolf, 1898-1986
General note
Conservation Note
This collection has been refiled and rehoused in acid-free folders and boxes. All metal fasteners were removed and replaced with plastic clips when necessary. Many brittle and torn items, primarily newspaper clippings, have been photocopied onto Permalife bond paper. After this process, original clippings were discarded.
If a deteriorating item was determined valuable in its original state, a white acid-free marker was placed in its folder. A list of these manuscripts has been compiled by series and will be submitted for in-house conservation.
The atomic bomb scrapbooks of Series XIII, Clippings, have been filed temporarily in Oversize Box #2. As the newspaper clippings are severely brittle, discolored, and torn, it is recommended that these scrapbooks be microfilmed when possible.
Note on Abbreviations
The following abbreviations appear throughout the container list:
AEC: Atomic Energy Commission
DSM: Development of Substitute Materials Project
EURATOM: European Atomic Energy Community
HDS: Henry DeWolf Smyth
IAEA: International Atomic Energy Commission
INDC: Interim International Nuclear Data Committee
JCAE: Joint Committee on Atomic Energy
JRO: J. Robert Oppenheimer
LASL: Los Alamos Scientific Laboratory
MdeCS: Mary de Coningh Smyth
n.d.: no date
NDRC: National Defense Research Committee
NPT: Nonproliferation Treaty
OSRD: Office of Scientific Research and Development
UNAEC: United Nations Atomic Energy Commission
UNO: United Nations Organization
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Smyth Papers were donated by Henry DeWolf Smyth in three major accessions. The first group of materials, approximately four file drawers and six cartons of publications, was presented by Smyth to the American Philosophical Society Library in July of 1982 and assigned accession #1982-881ms. The second gift of ca. twenty-eight linear feet was assigned accession #1987-1790ms. A third accession, ca. twenty linear feet, came after Smyth's death as a gift of his estate in February of 1987 and was assigned #1987-1789ms. Finally, three medals presented to Smyth were received by the library in June of 1987 from the Horizon Trust Company on behalf of Smyth's estate and assigned accession #1987-791me.
Scope and Contents note
The Henry DeWolf Smyth Papers (1885-1987) contain correspondence, subject files, speeches, manuscripts of unpublished and published works, reprints and printed publications, scientific class notes and papers, newspaper clippings, photographs, and memorabilia which document Smyth's career as a physicist and a statesman. The earliest piece in the collection is his father's Columbia College class photograph dating from 1885, while the most recent item is a transcript of Smyth's memorial service in 1987. The papers also contain materials generated by Mary de Coningh Smyth prior to and during her marriage to Henry Smyth; this includes her correspondence and diaries.
While the collection spans Smyth's lifetime, the bulk of the papers dates during his most active and influential career years, approximately 1944 to 1970. Smyth's most memorable achievements and associations occurred during these years, including his work on the Manhattan Project and the Smyth Report and his involvement with the U.S. AEC and the IAEA.
The papers (109 boxes; 54 linear feet) are divided into fifteen series:
Series I Professional Correspondence 19.5 linear feet
Series II General Subject Files 5 linear feet
Series III AEC Subject Files 2 linear feet
Series IV IAEA Subject Files 6.5 linear feet
Series V Smyth Report 4 boxes; 2 linear feet
Series VI Speeches and Testimonies
A. by HDS 2 linear feet
B. by Colleagues 1 linear foot
Series VII Manuscripts of Unpublished Works by HDS 0.5 linear feet
Series VIII Manuscripts of Published Works by HDS 1.5 linear feet
Series IX Reprints, Journals, and Publications 5.5 linear feet
Series X Class Notes and Papers
A. Taken by HDS 0.5 linear feet
B. Given by HDS 0.5 linear feet
Series XI Personal Correspondence 0.5 linear feet
Series XII Mary de Coningh Smyth Papers
A. Correspondence 2 linear feet
B. Diaries 2 linear feet
Series XIII Clippings 1 linear foot
Series XIV Photographs 1 linear foot
Series XV Memorabilia 0.5 linear feet
Series I-XV Oversize Materials 0.5 linear feet
Materials in oversize box #1 follow the same series arrangement as noted above. Unusual formats, such as rolled diplomas, certificates, and scrapbooks are located in oversize box #2. Cross referencing to these oversize boxes appears on the folders in the standard size boxes and on the container list.
Although the professional correspondence of Series I represents the largest part of the collection, other smaller series contain noteworthy material. Perhaps the most valuable papers to researchers will be found in Series V, relating to the Smyth Report. This series holds revealing correspondence and manuscript drafts relating to the written history of the Manhattan Project. Information which remained classified in 1945 and could not be included in the original edition of the Smyth Report has since been declassified and filed with Series V.
Researchers focusing on Smyth's career will also find material of note relating to his dissenting opinion in the Oppenheimer security case in Series VIII, Manuscripts of Published Works as well as Series I, Professional Correspondence. Other valuable aspects of the collection are the detailed diaries of Mary Smyth in Series XII; her entries record important dates, events, and commentary relating to her husband's career.
Biographical/Historical note
Henry DeWolf Smyth (1898-1986) was a physicist and diplomat who figured prominently in the development of atomic energy in the United States through his contributions as scientist, instructor, policy maker, administrator, and author. He is perhaps best known for writing the official government report on the development of the atomic bomb in the U.S., Atomic Energy for Military Purposes (1945). Smyth's other important contributions to the field of atomic science were made while a commissioner on the U.S. Atomic Energy Commission (AEC), from 1949 to 1954, and subsequently as the U.S. Representative to the International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA), from 1961 to 1970. These include his dissenting opinion in the AEC's security clearance case for J. Robert Oppenheimer, and his influential work with the IAEA on nonproliferation of nuclear weapons, and the peaceful use of atomic energy.
Henry DeWolf Smyth was born in Clinton, New York on 1 May 1898 to Charles Henry Smyth, Jr. and Ruth Anne Phelps. In 1905 the family moved to Princeton when Henry's father was appointed professor of geology. Henry attended Miss Fine's School, and the Lawrenceville School from which he was graduated in 1914. He went on to Princeton University graduating in 1918, and then pursued an independent research project with Karl Taylor Compton until 1919. His first paper, "Tyndall beam and size of particles," was published in July, 1919. Smyth worked in the chemical warfare laboratory in Washington, D.C. and at the Aberdeen Proving Ground until the end of World War I. He received his master's degree and Ph.D., both in physics, in quick succession at Princeton, 1920 and 1921 respectively. The faculty at Princeton made a special resolution to allow him to take his two examinations for the Ph.D. in one term.
As a National Research Council Fellow, he studied at the Cavendish Laboratory, Cambridge University, England, from 1921 to 1923, and at Princeton from 1923 to 1924. After his studies under Ernest Rutherford at the Cavendish, and a second doctorate, Smyth returned to Princeton where, in 1924, he became an instructor. He was named assistant professor in 1925, associate professor in 1929, professor in 1936. In 1935, he was named chairman of the physics department. Smyth married Mary de Coningh on 30 June 1936.
Smyth's primary research interests between 1919 and 1935 were the study of ionization of gases by electron impact and critical potentials, positive ray analysis, molecular structure, matter, motion and electricity, and atomic energy. He spent 1931-32 as a Guggenheim Fellow at the University of GC6ttingen. After 1934, his interests changed to nuclear physics with James Chadwick's discovery of the neutron, and the accelerator developments made by John Cockcroft and Ernest Walton, and by Ernest O. Lawrence. 1 The majority of his research papers were published between 1919 and 1945.
Following his appointment as chairman of the department in 1935, Smyth's administrative duties took precedence over his research. His colleague Val Fitch said of him, "he was unflappable and simply bristled with integrity. I have seen him on a number of occasions, by his presence alone, bring dignity to meetings which had all the ingredients of impending chaos." 2 Among Smyth's accomplishments at Princeton while he was chair of the physics department were the two cyclotrons which were both built by Milton G. White and his associates, the first in 1935, and the second in 1946.
In addition, Smyth devoted much effort to reorganizing the large introductory physics courses. He understood the importance of integrating teaching and research and, to this end, introduced the extensive use of lecture demonstrations. In 1939, his book Matter, Motion and Electricity was published. Co-written with Charles W. Ufford, it was "perhaps the first beginning text that attempted to cover the most recent physics in addition to the classical material." 3
Smyth's early career was primarily concerned with research on atomic structure. In 1940, before the Manhattan District was brought into being, he began his war work as a consultant on research programs for the National Research Council and the Office of Scientific Research and Development (OSRD). He continued this work until 1945.
Smyth was a member of the Uranium Committee which was a subcommittee of the National Defense Research Committee (NDRC). The NDRC, chaired by Vannevar Bush, was established 15 July 1940 to direct, coordinate and carry out a national program of military research and development. Its membership was drawn from the National Academy of Sciences. In June 1941, President Roosevelt established the OSRD with the NDRC as one of its subordinate agencies. Bush was made director of the OSRD and James B. Conant became chairman of the NDRC. The OSRD's aim was to mobilize American scientists for war. The Committee on Uranium, somewhat enlarged, remained under the NDRC but was renamed the Section on Uranium. 4
In order to maximize the effort to develop the atomic bomb, the atomic energy program was divorced from the NDRC in December 1941, and placed under the immediate supervision of Bush and the OSRD. This scientific group, now called the OSRD S-1 Section (the word "uranium" was dropped for security reasons), was to recommend and coordinate action on nuclear research and ensure that authorized assignments were carried out and, within 6 months, prepare a final report on the feasibility of building atomic bombs. In June 1942, the Army Corps of Engineers was directed to construct an atomic bomb with the OSRD retaining responsibility for scientific research and pilot plant experimentation for producing fissionable materials to be used in the manufacture of atomic bombs. 5
A member of the Uranium Committee under the National Defense Research Council, Smyth worked in the Uranium Section, the Power Production Subsection and the Theoretical Subsection which included Fermi, Szilard and J.A. Wheeler. "At that time he directed work at Princeton on resonance absorption of neutrons by U-238. In the fall of 1941 it was Smyth who suggested the use of large-scale electromagnetic methods to separate uranium isotopes, and by 1943 the first large amounts of U-235 had been separated by this method. As administrator, following the reorganization of the Uranium Committee of the NDRC under the Office of Scientific Research and Development in 1941, Smyth was appointed by the OSRD Uranium Committee Executive Group, which was to report on the program and budget for an eighteen-month period, `to prepare recommendations as to how many programs should be continued, and to prepare recommendations as to what parts of the program should be eliminated.'" 6
Between 1943 and 1945, he served as consultant to the Manhattan Engineer District, which produced the atomic bomb. From 1943-44 he was Assistant Director of, later consultant to, the Metallurgical Laboratory at the University of Chicago. There Arthur Compton's group worked on the production of the heavy water necessary to regulate the speed of neutrons in the chain reaction. Smyth, it should be remembered, continued to run Princeton's under-staffed physics department during the war.
In 1944, Lt. General Leslie Groves appointed Smyth to the Richard C. Tolman Committee to make recommendations for the post-war development of atomic energy. In spring of that year, Smyth suggested the need for an official report on the scientific and administrative operations of the atomic bomb project. In April, Groves asked Smyth to proceed with the report. He was permitted free access to all pertinent information, which meant that he was exempted from all normal compartmental rules, and visited each of the various departments of the Manhattan Engineering District, where he conferred with key people and collected data. He wrote the report in fifteen months under conditions of utmost secrecy. The official government report on the project was released on August 12th, 1945.
Made public after the bombings of Hiroshima and Nagasaki, Atomic Energy for Military Purposes, popularly known as the Smyth Report, was the first source of information on the atomic age for many Americans. The report was subsequently published in September 1945 by Princeton University Press, and sold more than 160,000 copies. Smyth had relinquished the copyright and received none of the royalties. The document itself was placed in the public domain, in accordance with Smyth's belief that "the ultimate responsibility for our nation's policy rests on its citizens and they can discharge such responsibilities wisely only if they are informed." 7
Between 1945 and 1949, Smyth, as Chairman, worked on strengthening the physics department. He was named the Joseph Henry Professor of Physics in 1946. In addition, from 1946 to 1949, he was a trustee to the Associated Universities Inc. which operated Brookhaven National Laboratory and the National Radio Astronomy Observatory. After 1945, his speeches and articles addressed the relation of science to government and to society, and three aspects of atomic energy: its historical development, its potential uses in peacetime, and the need for international control of future atomic energy development, since other nations had the capability to make atomic bombs.
In May 1949, he became a member of the Atomic Energy Commission, and gave up the chairmanship of the Princeton Physics Department the following year. Smyth was the only member of the AEC with a scientific background. President Truman appointed Smyth to a five-year term on the AEC in 1951. Smyth's duties while on the commission were to promote U.S. research in nuclear energy, and to plan U.S. development of peacetime nuclear power.
While on the AEC there were two notable events in which Smyth played an important role: the hydrogen bomb decision and the Oppenheimer case. Prior to 1949, although aware of the possibility of a fusion bomb (the H-bomb, or `Super'), the AEC had determined not to proceed with a full-scale development program. There was, however, a small research group working on the project. "The Soviet atomic bomb detonation in August 1949 brought pressure on the commission to commence such a program to ensure the U.S.'s military advantage. The AEC requested the opinion of the General Advisory Committee (consisting of 9 scientists and engineers with Oppenheimer as chairman), which in October 1949 unanimously opposed a crash program.
"On 1 November 1949 Senator Edwin Johnson stirred up the debate with his public announcement of the possibility of an H-bomb program." The AEC decided to let President Truman make the decision and submitted to the President the GAC recommendation and an opinion of each of the five AEC commissioners. "Chairman David E. Lilienthal, and Commissioners Sumner T. Pike and Smyth opposed a crash program; Commissioners Lewis L. Strauss and Gordon E. Dean favored it. Smyth saw this as an opportunity to open discussions on international control of atomic weapons, but on 31 January 1950, influenced by the reports of the departments of Defense and of State, Truman announced his decision to go ahead with the fusion bomb program." 8
J. Robert Oppenheimer, the chairman of the General Advisory Committee to the AEC, had headed the team that assembled and exploded the first atomic bomb at Los Alamos. During the height of the McCarthy era, Lewis Strauss, the Chairman of the AEC, expressed doubts about Oppenheimer's loyalty to the country and urged President Eisenhower to restrict his access to secret information. After Eisenhower had this "blank wall" erected, a Personnel Security Board hearing followed.
The hearing was conducted between April 12th and May 6th by Mr. Gordon Gray, Mr. Thomas Morgan, and Dr. Ward V. Evans. On May 27, 1954 the "Gray Board" recommended against Oppenheimer's reinstatement; Dr. Evans dissented. The Board also censured Oppenheimer for opposing the H-bomb program initially and for lacking enthusiasm for it afterwards. On May 28th Oppenheimer was notified of the board's decision, and on June 1st he waived his right to a Personnel Security Review. At this time he requested immediate consideration of his case by the Atomic Energy Commission. On June 12th, the General Manager reviewed the "Gray Board" testimony and submitted his conclusion to the Commission that Oppenheimer's clearance should not be reinstated.
Smyth writes, "In the first six months of 1954, I examined and evaluated the total evidence in the Oppenheimer Case. Allegations questioning the loyalty of Robert Oppenheimer were made in a letter to the FBI in the Fall of 1953. These allegations were made known by Lewis Strauss, Chairman of the Atomic Energy Commission, to his four fellow Commissioners for the first time on December 1, 1953. The matter occupied the Commission from that date until June 29, 1954 when the opinions of the five Commissioners were handed down. I was the sole Commissioner to vote in favor of restoring clearance to Robert Oppenheimer for reasons stated in my dissenting opinion of June 29, 1954" (See Series II, General Subject Files under Biographical information, June 1968, p.2).
The 1954 Oppenheimer clearance hearing resulted in a four-to-one vote against his reinstatement. Commissioners Strauss, Murray, Zuckert, and Campbell voted to revoke his clearance due to "defects of character." Smyth alone dissented from this opinion. He argued that the "defects," six instances in which Oppenheimer's statements and testimony over a period of years had been contradictory, were trivial if not contrived and that Oppenheimer's contributions to the atomic energy program were far greater than any potential security risk he was alleged to pose. At Smyth's memorial service, I.I. Rabi noted that this was Smyth's finest hour, "one thinks of a supreme moment in a person's life when he stood against odds and did the right thing. That was Harry Smyth's fortune and Harry Smyth's greatness" (See Series VIb, Speeches and Testimonies by Colleagues under Memorial service in thanksgiving for the life of Henry Dewolf Smyth 1898-1986, p.7).
Smyth's term as a commissioner of the Atomic Energy Commission ended in 1954 with his voluntary resignation. His resignation was not due to, or in direct answer to, the Commission's final recommendation in the Oppenheimer case. Rather, he found it difficult to work effectively with the chairman Lewis Strauss for personal reasons.
After his resignation from the AEC, Smyth returned to Princeton where he became chairman of the Board of Scientific and Engineering Research, known after May 1959 as the University Research Board. He acted in this capacity until 1966. The board's concerns were developing policies and practices related to Federal support of research, to advise the President of the University, advising on major research projects (especially, the construction of the Princeton-University of Pennsylvania 3-GeV accelerator), and expansion of research on control for peaceful uses of the thermonuclear reaction of the H-bomb. In addition, the Board of Scientific and Engineering Research was interested in developing and promoting the concept of a new University Research Board to be drawn from all divisions of the University so as to assure wide faculty responsibility for acceptance and administration of all major grants and contracts. The University Research Board also oversaw the development of the Plasma Physics Laboratory and the cyclotron laboratory.
Other Princeton activities included serving as chairman of the Faculty Committee on the choice of a new president from 1956-57. He was also chairman of the Committee on Project Research and Inventions, the Higgins and Scientific Research Committees, and the Matterhorn Review Committee. Smyth was particularly interested in the goals and magnitude of the Matterhorn Project which sought to release the nuclear energy locked in the deuterium (heavy hydrogen) in the oceans. In order to release this energy, the deuterium gas must be raised to a temperature of a hundred million degrees. The Matterhorn Project's objectives were to heat deuterium gas to such a temperature, to contain it at that temperature, and to extract energy from it. Los Alamos Scientific Laboratory (LASL) and the Livermore Laboratory also worked on this project. Other Princeton concerns were the accelerator project and the problem of computing facilities for the university. Smyth's service to Princeton University ended in 1966 with his retirement as Professor of Physics, Emeritus.